Guide to the Charlotte Salisbury papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Charlotte Salisbury papers,
1925-2001
[Bulk Dates: 1965-1993].
Salisbury, Charlotte Y.
14 linear ft. (28 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1626
6913725
This collection is made up of the writings and personal files of Charlotte Salisbury, the wife of Pulitzer-prize-winning journalist Harrison Evans Salisbury (1908-1993).
Biographical Note
Charlotte Young Salisbury was born in Weston, Massachusetts in 1914. The daughter of prominent Massachusetts politician Benjamin Loring Young, she attended the Winsor School in Boston and the Dobbs School in Dobbs Ferry, New York. Salisbury went on to pursue a modeling career as a “Powers Girl” in the early 1930s. In 1934 she married Allston Boyer, with whom she had her first daughter, Charlotte Boyer Parkinson. Following a divorce five years later, she married her second husband John A. Rand and had three more children: Ellen Rand, Rosina Rand, and Curtis Rand. During World War II she moved around the country following her husband to various army camps.
Charlotte met Harrison Salisbury in 1955 at a talk he gave in Salisbury, Connecticut on his time spent as a New York Times correspondent in Moscow. The two developed a friendship, and they married in 1964 following Charlotte’s divorce from John Rand in 1959. Throughout their marriage they kept homes in New York City and in Taconic, Connecticut.
Shortly after their wedding, Charlotte began accompanying Harrison on many of his foreign travel assignments. Although she was not formally trained as a writer, she kept detailed diaries throughout her life, and she was able to use her talents for close observation and description to begin her career as an author. Her first book, Asian Diary (1967) documents her travels with Harrison to the areas surrounding China. The book reflects her strong anti-Vietnam War sentiments as she describes the negative impact the war has had on neighboring countries. Charlotte Salisbury followed up Asian Diary with a series of travel diaries describing subsequent journeys with her husband in the Soviet Union, China, and other parts of Asia. China Diary was particularly notable as one of the first accounts of everyday life and social conditions in Communist China after President Nixon’s visit in 1972. The Salisburys’ books reached a broad American audience eager to learn about Communist countries. Whereas Harrison’s work focused on political and historical intricacies, Charlotte’s sensitive but frank impressions captured both her own experiences as a foreign traveler and the character of the daily lives of the people she encountered. In addition to China Diary (1972), she published Russian Diary (1974), China Diary: After Mao (1977), and Tibetan Diary (1980). Charlotte also wrote the text for Sikkim: Mountaintop Kingdom in 1972, collaborating with the photographer Alice Kendall. This book differs from her others as a description of the history, culture, and politics of the tiny country of Sikkim rather than a personal travel account.
Salisbury’s writing career culminated in her final book Long March Diary: China Epic, which describes her and Harrison Salisbury’s successful attempt to retrace the route of Mao’s Long March of 1934 to 1935. This was a remarkable achievement for the aging couple. It was their longest journey yet, and they traveled to areas of interior China that had previously been inaccessible to Americans.
While Harrison Salisbury continued to travel and write up until his death in 1993, Charlotte claimed to prefer a quiet life tending to their house and gardens in Taconic. She continued to keep detailed personal diaries, but she did no more extensive traveling. Charlotte Salisbury died at age ninety-eight on April 25, 2012 in Salisbury, Connecticut.
Scope and Content
This collection is made up of the writings and personal files of Charlotte Salisbury. About half of the material relates to Salisbury's published travel diaries. This material includes manuscripts as well as correspondence and clippings related to the books. Another large portion of the collection is made up of Charlotte Salisbury's personal papers, including correspondence between herself and Harrison Salisbury and approximately thirty years of diaries and datebooks recording her everyday activities. Finally, there is some material documenting the career and commemoration of Harrison Salisbury. With a few exceptions, the majority of the material in the collection dates to after the couple was married in 1964.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in XII series:
Series I. Asian Diary
Series II. Russian Diary
Series III. Sikkim: Mountaintop Kingdom
Series IV. China Diary
Series V. China Diary: After Mao
Series VI. Tibetan Diary
Series VII. Long March Diary: China Epic
Series VIII. Other Writings and Professional Activity
Series IX. Personal Files
Series X. Personal Correspondence
Series XI. Diaries and Datebooks
Series XII. Harrison E. Salisbury Files
Subjects
New York Times Company.; Salisbury, Charlotte Y.; Salisbury, Harrison E. (Harrison Evans), 1908-1993.; Asia--Description and travel.; China--Description and travel.; China--History--Long March, 1934-1935.; Soviet Union--Description and travel.; Soviet Union--Social conditions--1945-1991.; Silk Road--Description and travel.; Tibet Autonomous Region (China)--Description and travel.; Newspaper publishing.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least two business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Charlotte Young Salisbury Gift
Gift of Charlotte Young Salisbury.
- Series I: Asian Diary
  - Original notebooks, 1966, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts
    - Personal Copy, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Carbon copy, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Second Carbon copy, 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1966 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript fragments, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Galleys, 1966, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Photograph captions and descriptions, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Contract and royalties, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Sikkim article-Mademoiselle, 1967 (excerpt from Asian Diary ) (Box 2)
  - Clippings and reviews, 1968-1970, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Publicity, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1982 (Box 2)
- Series II: Russian Diary
  - Manuscripts (Box 3)
    - First Draft, 1967-1971, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1967 (Box 3)
    - Working Copy, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Personal Copy, 1967 (Box 3)
    - 1967-1972, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Fragments and edits, 1967-1972 (Box 4)
  - Cover and galleys, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Replaced chapter one, 1967-1972 (Box 4)
  - Notes and clippings, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Publicity, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Clippings and reviews, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1978 (Box 4)
- Series III: Sikkim: Mountaintop Kingdom
  - Notebooks, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Manuscripts
    - Draft, 1970 (Box 5)
    - With notes and corrections, 1970 (Box 5)
    - With introduction by Harrison Salisbury, 1970 (duplicate) (Box 5)
    - Corrected, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Contracts and royalties, 1969-1972 (Box 5)
  - Clippings regarding Sikkim and Hope Cooke, 1961-1974 (Box 5)
  - Notes and research materials, 1968-1970 (Box 5)
  - Research materials, 1950-1969 (Box 6)
  - Books
    - Sikkim Coronation, ca. 1965 (Box 6)
    - Namgyal Institute of Technology, 1962 (in Sikkimese) (Box 6)
  - Clippings and reviews, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - Publicity and Vogue article, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with Hope Cooke, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
- Series IV: China Diary
  - Original notebooks, 1972 (Box 7)
  - First typing from notebooks, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Manuscripts
    - Revised-out of order, 1972 (Box 7)
    - Xerox, 1972 (Box 7)
    - Edits, 1972 (Box 7)
    - 1972 (Box 7)
  - Galleys, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Notes and articles by Charlotte Salisbury regarding China Diary, 1973-1975 (Box 8)
  - Notes for chapter or article, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Travel materials, 1972, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Clippings related to China Diary- many New York Times articles by Harrison Salisbury, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Clippings and publicity, 1973 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1991 (Box 8)
- Series V: China Diary: After Mao
  - Original notebooks, 1977, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Manuscripts
    - Revised, 1977, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - With notes, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Notes regarding Mongolia, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Maps, ca. 1977 (Box 9)
  - Notes and clippings, 1978 (Box 9)
  - Clippings and publicity, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
- Series VI: Tibetan Diary
  - Manuscripts (Box 10)
    - Copy of first copying, 1980 (includes newspaper clipping) (Box 10)
    - Not all corrections included, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Working copy, 1980-1981 (Box 10)
    - Setting copy, 1980-1982 (Box 10)
  - Galleys, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Notes and travel materials, 1980-1981 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, photos, and publicity, 1980-1986 (Box 10)
- Series VII: Long MarchDiary: China Epic
  - Original notebooks, 1984 (Box 11)
  - Manuscripts
    - Original, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Second sheets of original, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Xerox with Harrison Salisbury foreword, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Carbon copy, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - With corrections by Jack Service, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - With corrections but not cuts, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - Edited, 1984-1986, (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Copy of book, 1992 (Box 13)
  - Map, ca. 1984 (Box 13)
  - Notes and photos, 1984-1985 (Box 13)
  - Notes for talks, ca. 1986 (Box 13)
  - Reviews and publicity, 1986 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence
    - Business, 1985-1986 (Box 13)
    - Personal, 1985-1993, (2 folders) (Box 13)
- Series VIII: Other Writings and Professional Activity
  - Articles and writings, ca. 1931-1982, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Webetuck School commencement, 1977 (Box 14)
  - Public appearances-general, 1978-1980 (Box 14)
  - Writer’s World radio program, 1969 (Box 14)
- Series IX: Personal Files
  - Passports and international travel documents, 1959-1986 (Box 14)
  - Biographical files-general, ca. 1925-1982 (includes financial agreement with Harrison Salisbury) (Box 14)
  - Personal photographs and postcards, ca. 1970s-1994 (Box 14)
  - Files regarding Francis Sargent-governor of Massachusetts 1972-1974 1969-1974 (Box 14)
  - Saved publications, 1953-2001 (Box 14)
  - The American Society of the Most Venerable Order of the Hospital of St. John of Jerusalem-Pins and list of members, 1975 (Box 28)
  - Scrapbook pages, 1977-1978 (Box 28)
- Series X: Personal Correspondence
  - Letters and cards from wedding, 1964 (Box 14)
  - Christmas-mostly cards, 1967 (Box 14)
  - Harrison Salisbury to Charlotte Salisbury (Box 15)
    - Notes and cards, ca. 1959-1986 (Box 15)
    - 1961-1987, (5 folders) (Box 15)
    - 1988-1993, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Charlotte Salisbury to Harrison Salisbury, 1959-1989, (4 folders) (Box 16)
  - General
    - Charlotte Salisbury, 1963-1998 (Box 16)
    - Harrison Salisbury, 1962-1990 (Box 16)
- Series XI: Diaries and Datebooks
  - Datebooks, 1969-1993, (6 folders) (Box 17)
  - Diaries, 1965-June 1993 (June 1968-June 1973 include typed transcripts) (Box 18-23)
- Series XII: Harrison Salisbury Files
  - Notes-mainly regarding Charlotte Salisbury’s biography, 1984-1988 (Box 24)
  - Lectures on QE2 voyages, 1978 (Box 24)
  - Vietnam tapes, ca. 1966-1967 (Box 24)
  - Personal papers-general, 1986-1991 (Box 24)
  - Litchfield County Writers’ Forum-Tribute to Harrison Salisbury, 1995-1996 (Box 24)
  - Thank you from Chinese People’s Revolutionary Museum for pacemaker donation, 1996 (Box 24)
  - Photographs of reception of pacemaker in China, ca. 1996 (Box 24)
  - Commemoration of Harrison Salisbury, 1991-1999 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence regarding Harrison Salisbury tribute book, 2001 (Box 24)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters-commemoration of Harrison Salisbury, 1993 (Box 25)
  - Dutch Treat Club member book, 1993 (Box 25)
  - Books
    - Essential Liberty by Francis Wilkinson-introduction by Harrison Salisbury (Box 25)
    - Long March: An Untold Story by Harrison Salisbury-Chinese translation, 1994 (Box 25)
    - Paper Soldiers by Lawrence R. Wyatt, 1992 (Box 25)
    - The Paper’s Papers by Richard F. Shepard, 1996 (Box 25)
    - A Journey for Our Times by Harrison Salisbury, 1983 (Box 26)
  - The 900 Days by Harrison Salisbury
    - Galleys-set 1, 1969, (4 folders) (Box 26)
    - Galleys-set 2, 1969, (5 folders) (Box 27)
  - Photographs-professional activity (mostly oversized) (Box 28)
  - Map-route of Mao’s Long March, 1984 (framed) (Box 28)
  - Russian records, ca. 1981-1985 (2) (Box 28)
  - The New York Times Magazine-with article by Harrison Salisbury-“Now It’s China’s Cultural Thaw,” 1977 (Box 28)